Chapter 50. Ahab's boat and crew.
Fidala.
Who would have thought at Flask? cried Stub. If I had but one leg, you would
not catch me in a boat. Unless maybe to stop the plug hole with my timber toe.
He is a wonderful old man. I don't think it's so strange after all on that
account, said Flask. If his leg were off at the hip now, it would be a different
thing. That would disable him. But he has one knee and a good part of the
other left, you know.
I don't know that, my little man. I never yet saw him kneel.
Among whalewise people, it has often been argued whether, considering the
paramount importance of his life to the success of the voyage, it is right for a
whailing captain to jeopardize that life in the active perils of the chase. So
Tamarlain soldiers often argued with tears in their eyes whether that
invaluable life of his ought to be carried into the thickest of the fight.
But with Ahab the question assumed a modified aspect, considering that with
two legs man is but a hobbling white in all times of danger, considering that
the pursuit of whales is always under great and extraordinary difficulties,
that every individual moment indeed then comprises apparel. Under these
circumstances, is it wise for any maimed man to enter a whaleboat in the hunt? As
a general thing, the joint owners of the Peekquad must plainly have thought not.
Ahab well knew that although his friends at home would think little of his
entering a boat in certain comparatively harmless vicissitudes of the chase for
the sake of being near the scene of action and giving his orders in person,
yet for Captain Ahab to have a boat actually aortioned to him as a regular
headsman in the hunt, above all for Captain Ahab to be supplied with five
extra men as that same boat's crew. He well knew that such generous conceits
never entered the heads of the owners of the Peekquad. Therefore, he had not
solicited a boat's crew from them, nor had he in any way hinted his desires on
that head. Nevertheless, he had taken private measures of his own touching all
that matter. Until Archie's published discovery, the sailors had little
foreseen it, though to be sure when, after being a little while out of port,
all hands had concluded the customary business of fitting the whaleboats for
service, when sometime after this Ahab was now and then found beering himself
in the matter of making thole pins with his own hands for what was thought to be
one of the spare boats, and even solicitously cutting the small wooden
skewers, which when the line is running out, are pinned over the groove in the
bow. When all this was observed in him, and particularly his solicitude in
having an extra coat of sheathing in the bottom of the boat, as if to make it
better withstand the pointed pressure of his ivory limb, and also the anxiety
heed in exactly shaping the thighboard, or clumsy cleat, as it is sometimes
called, the horizontal piece in the boat's bow for bracing the knee against,
in darting or stabbing at the whale, when it was observed how often he stood
up in that boat with his solitary knee fixed in the semic-ircular depression in
the cleat, and with the carpenter's chisel, gouged out a little here, and
straightened it a little there. All these things, I say, had awakened much
interest and curiosity at the time. But almost everybody supposed that this
particular preparative heedfulness in Ahab must only be with a view to the
ultimate chase of Moby Dick, for he had already revealed his intention to hunt
that mortal monster in person. But such a supposition did by no means involve
the remotest suspicion as to any boat's crew being assigned to that boat.
Now with these subordinate phantoms, what wonder remained soon waned away,
for in a wher wonders soon Wayne.
Besides, now and then such unaccountable odds and ends of strange nations come up
from the unknown nooks and ash holes of the earth to man these floating outlaws
of whalers, and the ships themselves often pick up such queer castaway
creatures found tossing about the open sea on planks, bits of wreck, orars,
whaleboats, canoes, blown off Japanese junks and whatnot, that Bezabub himself
might climb up the side and step down into the cabin. to chat with the
captain, and it would not create any unsubduable excitement in the folks.
But be all this as it may, certain it is, that while these subordinate
phantoms soon found their place among the crew, though still, as it were,
somehow distinct from them, yet that hair turbaned Fidala remained a muffled
mystery to the last. Once he came in a mannerly world like this, by what sort
of unaccountable tie he soon evinced himself to be linked with Ahab's
peculiar fortunes, nay, so far as to have some sort of half-hinted influence,
heaven knows, but it might have been even authority over him. All this none
knew, but one cannot sustain an indifferent heir concerning Fidala. He
was such a creature as civilized domestic people in the temperate zone
only see in their dreams, and that but dimly, but the like of whom now and then
glide among the unchanging Asiatic communities, especially the oriental
isles to the east of the continent, those insulated, immemorial, unalterable
countries, which even in these modern days still preserve much of the ghostly
aborigeness of the Earth's primal generations. when the memory of the
first man was a distinct recollection, and all men his descendants, unknowing
whence he came, eyed each other as real phantoms, and asked of the sun and the
moon why they were created, and to what end, when, though, according to Genesis,
the angels indeed consorted with the daughters of men, the devils also, add
the unconical rabbines, indulged in mundane amors.